Nathen Byford Resume

Status: Statistical Consultant for Statistical Consulting Center, Baylor University

Field: Data Science, Statistical Analysis, Spatial Statistics Techs: R, bash, Python, Regression Modeling, Machine Learning $Waco, \ Texas \\ nateby for d. com \\ nathen by ford@gmail.com$

Summary

Ph.D. student at Baylor University working on projects in spatial statistics, anomaly detection, bayesian modeling, and computational statistics. In addition to working on research I also work for the statistical consulting center helping clients from a wide range of fields from social work to geosciences. Experienced in data manipulation, data visualization, and multiple modeling techniques.

Experience

Statistical Consultant - Statistical Consulting Center, Baylor University

Sep. 2023 - Present

- * Perform statistical analysis for diverse range of clients and projects
- * Analyses of large scale and unstructured data sets with R and Bash
- * Present restults in clear and elementary manner for clients

Graduate Teaching Assistant - Baylor University

Aug. 2022 - Aug. 2024

- * Teach suplimental instruction sessions for introduction to statistics
- * Hold office hours for introcutory statistics and statistical methods
- * Grade homework, quizzes, and exams

Undergraduate Researcher - Oregon State University

June 2021 - Aug. 2021

- * Developing new methods to test for Benford's law in real data
- * Implementing methods in R
- * Comparing tests for greatest power and lowest error rate
- * Also look into Benfor's law in english words and texts

Data Science Fellow - Baylor University

June 2020 - Aug. 2020

- * Worked directly with stakeholders at Denver Water to analyze effectives and efficiency of water filtration
- * Produce statistical analysis and interpret results

Education

Ph.D. in Statistical Science - Waco, Texas

Aug. 2022 - Present

- * Project: Correcting for under reporting in Bayesian Spatial Scan Statistics
- * Developing and implementing Bayesian method to model under-reported and over-dispersed spatial counts

Master of Science in Statistical Science - Waco, Texas

Aug. 2022 - Dec. 2023

- * Project: Anomaly Detection in Time Series Data
- * Focus on Statistical Methods, Mathematical Statistics, and Computational Statistics.

Bachelor of Science in Statistical Science - Waco, Texas

Aug. 2019 - May 2022

* Major Courses: Mathematical Statistics, Computational Statistics, Database Design.

Interdisciplinary Collaborations

Analysis of Results for Social Work Dissertation - Consulting project

- Dec. 2023 Apr. 2024
- * Work alongside PhD candidate in Social Work to complete statistical analysis for dissertation.
- * Analyze survey results with descriptive statistics and logistic regression with model selection
- * Communicate results clearly to client along with methods

Projects

Spatial Under-Reporting of COVID-19 - Spatial Statistics final project

May 2024

- * Project: Correcting under-reporting in over-dispersed spatial count data
- * Developing and implementing Bayesian method to model under-reported and over-dispersed spatial counts

Anomaly Detection in Time Series Data - Baylor University

Dec. 2023

- * Anomaly detection using data driven methods
- * Methods include; regression leverage points, STL, neural network, and isolation forest

Capstone project (Planarian Growth) - Baylor University

May 2022

- * Worked with freshmen in BIO 1406 as statistical consultant
- * Analyzed the growth of planarian based on light exposure
- * Guided students from experimental design through to presentation of results